<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" >
<!-- SPDX-License-Identifier: LGPL-2.1-or-later -->

<refentry id="org.freedesktop.home1" conditional='ENABLE_HOMED'
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <refentryinfo>
    <title>org.freedesktop.home1</title>
    <productname>systemd</productname>
  </refentryinfo>

  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>org.freedesktop.home1</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>org.freedesktop.home1</refname>
    <refpurpose>The D-Bus interface of systemd-homed</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para><citerefentry><refentrytitle>systemd-homed.service</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>
    is a system service which may be used to create, remove, change or inspect home areas. This page
    describes the D-Bus interface.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>The Manager Object</title>

    <para>The service exposes the following interfaces on the Manager object on the bus:</para>

    <programlisting executable="systemd-homed" node="/org/freedesktop/home1" interface="org.freedesktop.home1.Manager">
node /org/freedesktop/home1 {
  interface org.freedesktop.home1.Manager {
    methods:
      GetHomeByName(in  s user_name,
                    out u uid,
                    out s home_state,
                    out u gid,
                    out s real_name,
                    out s home_directory,
                    out s shell,
                    out o bus_path);
      GetHomeByUID(in  u uid,
                   out s user_name,
                   out s home_state,
                   out u gid,
                   out s real_name,
                   out s home_directory,
                   out s shell,
                   out o bus_path);
      GetUserRecordByName(in  s user_name,
                          out s user_record,
                          out b incomplete,
                          out o bus_path);
      GetUserRecordByUID(in  u uid,
                         out s user_record,
                         out b incomplete,
                         out o bus_path);
      ListHomes(out a(susussso) home_areas);
      @org.freedesktop.systemd1.Privileged("true")
      ActivateHome(in  s user_name,
                   in  s secret);
      @org.freedesktop.systemd1.Privileged("true")
      DeactivateHome(in  s user_name);
      RegisterHome(in  s user_record);
      UnregisterHome(in  s user_name);
      CreateHome(in  s user_record);
      RealizeHome(in  s user_name,
                  in  s secret);
      RemoveHome(in  s user_name);
      @org.freedesktop.systemd1.Privileged("true")
      FixateHome(in  s user_name,
                 in  s secret);
      AuthenticateHome(in  s user_name,
                       in  s secret);
      UpdateHome(in  s user_record);
      ResizeHome(in  s user_name,
                 in  t size,
                 in  s secret);
      ChangePasswordHome(in  s user_name,
                         in  s new_secret,
                         in  s old_secret);
      @org.freedesktop.systemd1.Privileged("true")
      LockHome(in  s user_name);
      @org.freedesktop.systemd1.Privileged("true")
      UnlockHome(in  s user_name,
                 in  s secret);
      AcquireHome(in  s user_name,
                  in  s secret,
                  in  b please_suspend,
                  out h send_fd);
      @org.freedesktop.systemd1.Privileged("true")
      RefHome(in  s user_name,
              in  b please_suspend,
              out h send_fd);
      @org.freedesktop.systemd1.Privileged("true")
      ReleaseHome(in  s user_name);
      @org.freedesktop.systemd1.Privileged("true")
      LockAllHomes();
      @org.freedesktop.systemd1.Privileged("true")
      DeactivateAllHomes();
      @org.freedesktop.systemd1.Privileged("true")
      Rebalance();
    properties:
      readonly a(sso) AutoLogin = [...];
  };
  interface org.freedesktop.DBus.Peer { ... };
  interface org.freedesktop.DBus.Introspectable { ... };
  interface org.freedesktop.DBus.Properties { ... };
};
    </programlisting>

    <!--Autogenerated cross-references for systemd.directives, do not edit-->

    <variablelist class="dbus-interface" generated="True" extra-ref="org.freedesktop.home1.Manager"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-interface" generated="True" extra-ref="org.freedesktop.home1.Manager"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="GetHomeByName()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="GetHomeByUID()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="GetUserRecordByName()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="GetUserRecordByUID()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="ListHomes()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="ActivateHome()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="DeactivateHome()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="RegisterHome()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="UnregisterHome()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="CreateHome()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="RealizeHome()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="RemoveHome()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="FixateHome()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="AuthenticateHome()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="UpdateHome()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="ResizeHome()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="ChangePasswordHome()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="LockHome()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="UnlockHome()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="AcquireHome()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="RefHome()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="ReleaseHome()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="LockAllHomes()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="DeactivateAllHomes()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="Rebalance()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-property" generated="True" extra-ref="AutoLogin"/>

    <!--End of Autogenerated section-->

    <refsect2>
      <title>Methods</title>

      <para><function>GetHomeByName()</function> returns basic user information (a minimal subset of the full
      user record), provided a user name. The information supplied more or less matches what
      <citerefentry project="man-pages"><refentrytitle>getpwnam</refentrytitle><manvolnum>3</manvolnum></citerefentry> returns:
      the numeric UID and GID, the real name, home directory and shell. In addition it returns a state
      identifier describing the state the user's home directory is in, as well as a bus path referring to the
      bus object encapsulating the user record and home directory. This object implements the
      <classname>org.freedesktop.home1.Home</classname> interface documented below.</para>

      <para><function>GetHomeByUID()</function> is similar to <function>GetHomeByName()</function> but
      acquires the information based on the numeric UID of the user.</para>

      <para><function>GetUserRecordByName()</function> is also similar to
      <function>GetHomeByName()</function> but returns the full JSON user record data instead of the broken
      down records. An additional returned boolean indicates whether the record is complete or not. A record
      is considered complete when its <literal>privileged</literal> section is included, and incomplete if it
      was removed (see <ulink url="https://systemd.io/USER_RECORD">JSON User Records</ulink> for details
      about the various sections of a user record). Generally, only privileged clients and clients running
      under the identity of the user itself get access to the <literal>privileged</literal> section and will
      thus see complete records.</para>

      <para><function>GetUserRecordByUID()</function> is similar to <function>GetUserRecordByName()</function>
      but returns the user record matching the specified numeric UID.</para>

      <para><function>ListHomes()</function> returns an array of all locally managed users. The array
      contains the same fields <function>GetHomeByName()</function> returns: user name, numeric UID, state,
      numeric GID, real name, home directory, shell and bus path of the matching bus object.</para>

      <para><function>ActivateHome()</function> activates (i.e. mounts) the home directory of the specified
      user. The second argument shall contain a user record consisting only of a <literal>secret</literal>
      section (all other sections should be stripped, see <ulink url="https://systemd.io/USER_RECORD">JSON
      User Records</ulink> for details), and should contain only the secret credentials necessary for
      unlocking the home directory. Typically a client would invoke this function first with an entirely
      empty record (which is possibly sufficient if single-factor authentication with a plugged-in security
      token is configured), and would then retry with a record populated with more information, depending on
      the returned error code, in case more credentials are necessary. This function is synchronous and
      returns only after the home directory was fully activated (or the operation failed), which might take
      some time. Clients must be prepared for that, and typically should extend the D-Bus method call
      timeout accordingly. This method is equivalent to the <function>Activate()</function> method on the
      <classname>org.freedesktop.home1.Home</classname> interface documented below, but may be called on the
      manager object and takes a user name as additional argument, instead.</para>

      <para><function>DeactivateHome()</function> deactivates (i.e. unmounts) the home directory of the
      specified user. It is equivalent to the <function>Deactivate()</function> method on the
      <classname>org.freedesktop.home1.Home</classname> interface documented below.</para>

      <para><function>RegisterHome()</function> registers a new home directory locally. It receives the JSON
      user record as only argument (which typically excludes the <literal>secret</literal>
      section). Registering a home directory just makes the user record known to the system, it does not
      create a home directory or such (which is expected to exist already, or created later). This operation
      is useful to register home directories locally that are not located where
      <filename>systemd-homed.service</filename> would find them automatically.</para>

      <para><function>UnregisterHome()</function> unregisters an existing home directory. It takes a user
      name as argument and undoes what <function>RegisterHome()</function> does. It does not attempt to
      remove the home directory itself, it just unregisters it with the local system. Note that if the home
      directory is placed where <filename>systemd-homed.service</filename> looks for home directories anyway
      this call will only undo fixation (see below), but the record will remain known to
      <filename>systemd-homed.service</filename> and be listed among known records. Since the user record is
      embedded into the home directory this operation generally does not discard data belonging to the user
      or their record. This method is equivalent to
      <function>Unregister()</function> on the <classname>org.freedesktop.home1.Home</classname>
      interface.</para>

      <para><function>CreateHome()</function> registers and creates a new home directory. This takes a fully
      specified JSON user record as argument (including the <literal>secret</literal> section). This registers
      the user record locally and creates a home directory matching it, depending on the settings specified
      in the record in combination with local configuration.</para>

      <para><function>RealizeHome()</function> creates a home directory whose user record is already
      registered locally. This takes a user name plus a user record consisting only of the
      <literal>secret</literal> section. Invoking <function>RegisterHome()</function> followed by
      <function>RealizeHome()</function> is mostly equivalent to calling <function>CreateHome()</function>,
      except that the latter combines the two in atomic fashion. This method is equivalent to
      <function>Realize()</function> on the <classname>org.freedesktop.home1.Home</classname>
      interface.</para>

      <para><function>RemoveHome()</function> unregisters a user record locally, and removes the home
      directory belonging to it, if it is accessible. It takes a user name as argument. This method is equivalent to
      <function>Remove()</function> on the <classname>org.freedesktop.home1.Home</classname>
      interface.</para>

      <para><function>FixateHome()</function> <literal>fixates</literal> an automatically discovered home
      directory. <filename>systemd-homed.service</filename> automatically discovers home directories dropped
      in our plugged in and adds them to the runtime list of user records it manages. A user record
      discovered that way may be <literal>fixated</literal>, in which case it is copied out of the home
      directory, onto persistent storage, to fixate the UID/GID assignment of the record, and extract
      additional (typically previously encrypted) user record data from the home directory. A home directory
      mus be fixated before it can be logged into. This method call takes a user name and a JSON user record
      consisting only of the <literal>secret</literal> section as argument. This method is equivalent to
      <function>Fixate()</function> on the <classname>org.freedesktop.home1.Home</classname> interface.</para>

      <para><function>AuthenticateHome()</function> checks passwords or other authentication credentials
      associated with the home directory. It takes a user name and a JSON user record consisting only of the
      <literal>secret</literal> section as argument. Note that many of the other method calls authenticate
      the user first, in order to execute some other operation. This method call only authenticates and
      executes no further operation. Like <function>ActivateHome()</function> it is usually first invoked
      with an empty JSON user record, which is then populated for subsequent tries with additional
      authentication data supplied. This method is equivalent to
      <function>Authenticate()</function> on the <classname>org.freedesktop.home1.Home</classname>
      interface.</para>

      <para><function>UpdateHome()</function> updates a locally registered user record. Takes a fully
      specified JSON user record as argument (including the <literal>secret</literal> section). A user with a
      matching name and realm must be registered locally already, and the last change timestamp of the newly
      supplied record must be newer than the previously existing user record. Note this operation updates the
      user record only, it does not propagate passwords/authentication tokens from the user record to the
      storage back-end, or resizes the storage back-end. Typically a home directory is first updated, and then
      the password of the underlying storage updated using <function>ChangePasswordHome()</function> as well
      as the storage resized using <function>ResizeHome()</function>. This method is equivalent to
      <function>Update()</function> on the <classname>org.freedesktop.home1.Home</classname> interface.</para>

      <para><function>ResizeHome()</function> resizes the storage associated with a user record. Takes a user
      name, a disk size in bytes and a user record consisting only of the <literal>secret</literal> section
      as argument. If the size is specified as <constant>UINT64_MAX</constant> the storage is resized to the
      size already specified in the user record. Typically, if the user record is updated using
      <function>UpdateHome()</function> above this is used to propagate the size configured there-in down to
      the underlying storage back-end. This method is equivalent to
      <function>Resize()</function> on the <classname>org.freedesktop.home1.Home</classname>
      interface.</para>

      <para><function>ChangePasswordHome()</function> changes the passwords/authentication tokens of a home
      directory. Takes a user name, and two JSON user record objects, each consisting only of the
      <literal>secret</literal> section, for the old and for the new passwords/authentication tokens. If the
      user record with the new passwords/authentication token data is specified as empty the existing user
      record's settings are propagated down to the home directory storage. This is typically used after a
      user record is updated using <function>UpdateHome()</function> in order to propagate the
      secrets/authentication tokens down to the storage. Background: depending on the backend the user's
      authentication credentials are stored at multiple places: the user record kept on the host, the user
      record kept in the home directory and the encrypted LUKS volume slot. If the home directory is used on
      a different machined temporarily, and the password is changed there, and then is moved back to the
      original host, the passwords of the three might get out of sync. By issuing
      <function>ChangePasswordHome()</function> the three locations are updated to match the newest
      information. This method is equivalent to <function>ChangePassword()</function> on the
      <classname>org.freedesktop.home1.Home</classname> interface.</para>

      <para><function>LockHome()</function> temporarily suspends access to a home directory, flushing out any
      cryptographic keys from memory. This is only supported on some back-ends, and usually done during system
      suspend, in order to effectively secure home directories while the system is sleeping. Takes a user
      name as single argument. If an application attempts to access a home directory while it is locked it
      will typically freeze until the home directory is unlocked again. This method is equivalent to
      <function>Lock()</function> on the <classname>org.freedesktop.home1.Home</classname> interface.</para>

      <para><function>UnlockHome()</function> undoes the effect of <function>LockHome()</function>. Takes a
      user name and a user record consisting only of the <literal>secret</literal> section as arguments. This
      method is equivalent to <function>Unlock()</function> on the
      <classname>org.freedesktop.home1.Home</classname> interface.</para>

      <para><function>AcquireHome()</function> activates or unlocks a home directory in a reference counted
      mode of operation. Takes a user name and user record consisting only of <literal>secret</literal>
      section as argument. If the home directory is not active yet, it is activated. If it is currently
      locked it is unlocked. After completion a reference to the activation/unlocking of the home directory
      is returned via a file descriptor. When the last client which acquired such a file descriptor closes it
      the home directory is automatically deactivated again. This method is typically invoked when a user
      logs in, and the file descriptor is held until the user logs out again, thus ensuring the user's home
      directory can be unmounted automatically again in a robust fashion, when the user logs out. The third
      argument is a boolean which indicates whether the client invoking the call is able to automatically
      re-authenticate when the system comes back from suspending. It should be set by all clients that
      implement a secure lock screen running outside of the user's context, that is brought up when the
      system comes back from suspend and can be used to re-acquire the credentials to unlock the user's home
      directory. If a home directory has at least one client with an open reference to the home directory
      that does not support this it is not suspended automatically at system suspend, otherwise it is. This
      method is equivalent to <function>Acquire()</function> on the
      <classname>org.freedesktop.home1.Home</classname> interface.</para>

      <para><function>RefHome()</function> is similar to <function>AcquireHome()</function> but takes no user
      record with <literal>secret</literal> section, i.e. will take an additional reference to an already
      activated/unlocked home directory without attempting to activate/unlock it itself. It will fail if the
      home directory is not already activated. This method is equivalent to
      <function>Ref()</function> on the <classname>org.freedesktop.home1.Home</classname>
      interface.</para>

      <para><function>ReleaseHome()</function> releases a home directory again, if all file descriptors
      referencing it are already closed, that where acquired through <function>AcquireHome()</function> or
      <function>RefHome()</function>. Note that this call does not actually cause the deactivation of the
      home directory (which happens automatically when the last referencing file descriptor is closed), but
      is simply a synchronization mechanism that allows delaying of the user session's termination until any
      triggered deactivation is completed. This method is equivalent to <function>Release()</function> on the
      <classname>org.freedesktop.home1.Home</classname> interface.</para>

      <para><function>LockAllHomes()</function> locks all active home directories that only have references
      that opted into automatic suspending during system suspend. This is usually invoked automatically
      shortly before system suspend.</para>

      <para><function>DeactivateAllHomes()</function> deactivates all home areas that are currently
      active. This is usually invoked automatically shortly before system shutdown.</para>

      <para><function>Rebalance()</function> synchronously rebalances free disk space between home
      areas. This only executes an operation if at least one home area using the LUKS2 backend is active and
      has rebalancing enabled, and is otherwise a NOP.</para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Properties</title>

      <para><varname>AutoLogin</varname> exposes an array of structures consisting of user name, seat name
      and object path of an home directory object. All locally managed users that have the
      <literal>autoLogin</literal> field set are listed here, with the seat name they are associated with. A
      display manager may watch this property and pre-fill the login screen with the users exposed this
      way.</para>
    </refsect2>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>The Home Object</title>

    <programlisting executable="systemd-homed" node="/org/freedesktop/home1/home" interface="org.freedesktop.home1.Home">
node /org/freedesktop/home1/home {
  interface org.freedesktop.home1.Home {
    methods:
      @org.freedesktop.systemd1.Privileged("true")
      Activate(in  s secret);
      @org.freedesktop.systemd1.Privileged("true")
      Deactivate();
      Unregister();
      Realize(in  s secret);
      Remove();
      @org.freedesktop.systemd1.Privileged("true")
      Fixate(in  s secret);
      Authenticate(in  s secret);
      Update(in  s user_record);
      Resize(in  t size,
             in  s secret);
      ChangePassword(in  s new_secret,
                     in  s old_secret);
      @org.freedesktop.systemd1.Privileged("true")
      Lock();
      @org.freedesktop.systemd1.Privileged("true")
      Unlock(in  s secret);
      @org.freedesktop.systemd1.Privileged("true")
      Acquire(in  s secret,
              in  b please_suspend,
              out h send_fd);
      @org.freedesktop.systemd1.Privileged("true")
      Ref(in  b please_suspend,
          out h send_fd);
      @org.freedesktop.systemd1.Privileged("true")
      Release();
    properties:
      @org.freedesktop.DBus.Property.EmitsChangedSignal("const")
      readonly s UserName = '...';
      readonly u UID = ...;
      readonly (suusss) UnixRecord = ...;
      @org.freedesktop.DBus.Property.EmitsChangedSignal("false")
      readonly s State = '...';
      @org.freedesktop.DBus.Property.EmitsChangedSignal("invalidates")
      readonly (sb) UserRecord = ...;
  };
  interface org.freedesktop.DBus.Peer { ... };
  interface org.freedesktop.DBus.Introspectable { ... };
  interface org.freedesktop.DBus.Properties { ... };
  interface org.freedesktop.DBus.ObjectManager { ... };
};
    </programlisting>

    <!--Autogenerated cross-references for systemd.directives, do not edit-->

    <variablelist class="dbus-interface" generated="True" extra-ref="org.freedesktop.DBus.ObjectManager"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-interface" generated="True" extra-ref="org.freedesktop.home1.Home"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-interface" generated="True" extra-ref="org.freedesktop.DBus.ObjectManager"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-interface" generated="True" extra-ref="org.freedesktop.home1.Home"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="Activate()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="Deactivate()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="Unregister()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="Realize()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="Remove()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="Fixate()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="Authenticate()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="Update()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="Resize()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="ChangePassword()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="Lock()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="Unlock()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="Acquire()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="Ref()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="Release()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-property" generated="True" extra-ref="UserName"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-property" generated="True" extra-ref="UID"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-property" generated="True" extra-ref="UnixRecord"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-property" generated="True" extra-ref="State"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-property" generated="True" extra-ref="UserRecord"/>

    <!--End of Autogenerated section-->

    <refsect2>
      <title>Methods</title>

      <para><function>Activate()</function>, <function>Deactivate()</function>,
      <function>Unregister()</function>, <function>Realize()</function>, <function>Remove()</function>,
      <function>Fixate()</function>, <function>Authenticate()</function>, <function>Update()</function>,
      <function>Resize()</function>, <function>ChangePassword()</function>, <function>Lock()</function>,
      <function>Unlock()</function>, <function>Acquire()</function>, <function>Ref()</function>,
      <function>Release()</function> operate like their matching counterparts on the
      <classname>org.freedesktop.home1.Manager</classname> interface (see above). The main difference is that
      they are methods of the home directory objects, and hence carry no additional user name
      parameter. Which of the two flavors of methods to call depends on the handles to the user known on the
      client side: if only the user name is known, it's preferable to use the methods on the manager object
      since they operate with user names only. If however the home object path was already acquired some way
      it is preferable to operate on the <classname>org.freedesktop.home1.Home</classname> objects
      instead.</para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Properties</title>

      <para><varname>UserName</varname> contains the user name of the user account/home directory.</para>

      <para><varname>UID</varname> contains the numeric UNIX UID of the user account.</para>

      <para><varname>UnixRecord</varname> contains a structure encapsulating the six fields a
      <structname>struct passwd</structname> typically contains (the password field is suppressed).</para>

      <para><varname>State</varname> exposes the current state home the home directory.</para>

      <para><varname>UserRecord</varname> contains the full JSON user record string of the user account.</para>
    </refsect2>
  </refsect1>

  <xi:include href="org.freedesktop.locale1.xml" xpointer="versioning"/>

  <refsect1>
    <title>See Also</title>
    <para><simplelist type="inline">
      <member><citerefentry><refentrytitle>systemd</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></member>
      <member><citerefentry><refentrytitle>systemd-homed.service</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry></member>
      <member><citerefentry><refentrytitle>homectl</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></member>
    </simplelist></para>
  </refsect1>

</refentry>
