<?xml version='1.0'?> <!--*-nxml-*-->
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- SPDX-License-Identifier: LGPL-2.1-or-later -->

<refentry id="pam_systemd_home" conditional='ENABLE_PAM_HOME'
          xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

  <refentryinfo>
    <title>pam_systemd_home</title>
    <productname>systemd</productname>
  </refentryinfo>

  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>pam_systemd_home</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>pam_systemd_home</refname>
    <refpurpose>Authenticate users and mount home directories via <filename>systemd-homed.service</filename>
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para><filename>pam_systemd_home.so</filename></para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>

    <para><command>pam_systemd_home</command> ensures that home directories managed by
    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>systemd-homed.service</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>
    are automatically activated (mounted) on user login, and are deactivated (unmounted) when the last
    session of the user ends. For such users, it also provides authentication (when per-user disk encryption
    is used, the disk encryption key is derived from the authentication credential supplied at login time),
    account management (the <ulink url="https://systemd.io/USER_RECORD/">JSON user record</ulink> embedded in
    the home store contains account details), and implements the updating of the encryption password (which
    is also used for user authentication).</para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Options</title>

    <para>The following options are understood:</para>

    <variablelist class='pam-directives'>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><varname>suspend=</varname></term>

        <listitem><para>Takes a boolean argument. If true, the home directory of the user will be suspended
        automatically during system suspend; if false it will remain active. Automatic suspending of the home
        directory improves security substantially as secret key material is automatically removed from memory
        before the system is put to sleep and must be re-acquired (through user re-authentication) when
        coming back from suspend. It is recommended to set this parameter for all PAM applications that have
        support for automatically re-authenticating via PAM on system resume. If multiple sessions of the
        same user are open in parallel the user's home directory will be left unsuspended on system suspend
        as long as at least one of the sessions does not set this parameter to on. Defaults to
        off.</para>

        <para>Note that TTY logins generally do not support re-authentication on system resume.
        Re-authentication on system resume is primarily a concept implementable in graphical environments, in
        the form of lock screens brought up automatically when the system goes to sleep. This means that if a
        user concurrently uses graphical login sessions that implement the required re-authentication
        mechanism and console logins that do not, the home directory is not locked during suspend, due to the
        logic explained above. That said, it is possible to set this field for TTY logins too, ignoring the
        fact that TTY logins actually do not support the re-authentication mechanism. In that case the TTY
        sessions will appear hung until the user logs in on another virtual terminal (regardless of whether via
        another TTY session or graphically) which will resume the home directory and unblock the original TTY
        session. (Do note that lack of screen locking on TTY sessions means even though the TTY session
        appears hung, keypresses can still be queued into it, and the existing screen contents be read
        without re-authentication; this limitation is unrelated to the home directory management
        <command>pam_systemd_home</command> and <filename>systemd-homed.service</filename> implement.)</para>

        <para>Turning this option on by default is highly recommended for all sessions, but only if the
        service managing these sessions correctly implements the aforementioned re-authentication. Note that
        the re-authentication must take place from a component running outside of the user's context, so that
        it does not require access to the user's home directory for operation. Traditionally, most desktop
        environments do not implement screen locking this way, and need to be updated
        accordingly.</para>

        <para>This setting may also be controlled via the <varname>$SYSTEMD_HOME_SUSPEND</varname>
        environment variable (see below), which <command>pam_systemd_home</command> reads during initialization and sets
        for sessions. If both the environment variable is set and the module parameter specified the latter
        takes precedence.</para>

        <xi:include href="version-info.xml" xpointer="v245"/></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><varname>debug</varname><optional>=</optional></term>

        <listitem><para>Takes an optional boolean argument. If yes or without the argument, the module will log
        debugging information as it operates.</para>

        <xi:include href="version-info.xml" xpointer="v245"/></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Home Area Support</title>

    <para>Home directories managed by
    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>systemd-homed.service</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>
    support multiple home "areas", which are additional secondary home directories of the user within the
    primary home directory. An example: at login time if a user <literal>lennart</literal> with a home
    directory of <filename>/home/lennart</filename> specifies <literal>lennart%versuch1</literal> as account
    name during login, then <command>pam_systemd_home</command> will execute a login into
    <literal>lennart</literal> but ensure that the <varname>$HOME</varname> variable is set to
    <filename>/home/lennart/Areas/versuch1</filename> instead of the usual
    <filename>/home/lennart</filename>.</para>

    <para>This is particularly useful when sharing the same home directory between multiple systems (for
    example between a host and a VM), with the desire to share the home directory to a large degree, but
    still have separate session configuration in place.</para>

    <para>Note that the default area to log into can also be encoded in the user record, and it can be
    specified among
    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>pam_systemd</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>
    configuration parameters. However, an explicit area specified at login time (via the <literal>%</literal>
    described above) overrides any such default. Also note that simply suffixing an account with
    <literal>%</literal> at login time (i.e. specifying an empty area name) has the effect of ensuring a
    login into the primary home directory, overriding any default area configuration via the user record or
    PAM.</para>

    <para>Note that not all login mechanisms are compatible with the <literal>%</literal> syntax at login
    time. Most notably <citerefentry
    project='man-pages'><refentrytitle>ssh</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry> is not.</para>

    <para>Note that the area directory to log into must exist for the area specification to be respected. If
    an area is specified during login via the <literal>%</literal> logic (or the other mentioned mechanisms)
    and it does not actually exist the request will be ignored, and the user will log into the primary home
    directory instead.</para>

    <para>Typically, in order to make use of the mechanism set up an area first, like this:</para>

    <programlisting>lennart@zeta$ mkdir -p ~/Areas
lennart@zeta$ cp -av /etc/skel ~/Areas/versuch1</programlisting>

    <para>This should be enough to log into the newly created area, either via a regular terminal (using
    <literal>lennart%versuch1</literal> when prompted for a user name), or via
    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>run0</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>:</para>

    <programlisting>lennart@zeta$ run0 --area=versuch1</programlisting>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Module Types Provided</title>

    <para>The module implements all four PAM operations: <option>auth</option> (to allow authentication using
    the encrypted data), <option>account</option> (because users with
    <filename>systemd-homed.service</filename> user accounts are described in a <ulink
    url="https://systemd.io/USER_RECORD/">JSON user record</ulink> and may be configured in more detail than
    in the traditional Linux user database), <option>session</option> (because user sessions must be tracked
    in order to implement automatic release when the last session of the user is gone),
    <option>password</option> (to change the encryption password — also used for user authentication —
    through PAM).</para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Environment</title>

    <para>The following environment variables are initialized by the module and available to the processes of the
    user's session:</para>

    <variablelist class='environment-variables'>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><varname>$SYSTEMD_HOME=1</varname></term>

        <listitem><para>Indicates that the user's home directory is managed by <filename>systemd-homed.service</filename>.</para>

        <xi:include href="version-info.xml" xpointer="v245"/></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><varname>$SYSTEMD_HOME_SUSPEND=</varname></term>

        <listitem><para>Indicates whether the session has been registered with the suspend mechanism enabled
        or disabled (see above). The variable's value is either <literal>0</literal> or
        <literal>1</literal>. Note that the module both reads the variable when initializing, and sets it for
        sessions.</para>

        <xi:include href="version-info.xml" xpointer="v246"/></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Example</title>

    <para>Here's an example PAM configuration fragment that permits users managed by
    <filename>systemd-homed.service</filename> to log in:</para>

    <programlisting>#%PAM-1.0
    <command>-auth     [success=done authtok_err=bad perm_denied=bad maxtries=bad default=ignore] pam_systemd_home.so</command>
auth      sufficient pam_unix.so
auth      required   pam_deny.so

account   required   pam_nologin.so
<command>-account  [success=done authtok_expired=bad new_authtok_reqd=bad maxtries=bad acct_expired=bad default=ignore] pam_systemd_home.so</command>
account   required   pam_unix.so

<command>-password sufficient pam_systemd_home.so</command>
password  sufficient pam_unix.so sha512 shadow try_first_pass
password  required   pam_deny.so

-session  optional   pam_keyinit.so revoke
-session  optional   pam_loginuid.so
<command>-session  optional   pam_systemd_home.so</command>
-session  optional   pam_systemd.so
session   required   pam_unix.so</programlisting>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>See Also</title>
    <para><simplelist type="inline">
      <member><citerefentry><refentrytitle>systemd</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></member>
      <member><citerefentry><refentrytitle>systemd-homed.service</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry></member>
      <member><citerefentry><refentrytitle>homed.conf</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry></member>
      <member><citerefentry><refentrytitle>homectl</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></member>
      <member><citerefentry><refentrytitle>pam_systemd</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry></member>
      <member><citerefentry project='man-pages'><refentrytitle>pam.conf</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry></member>
      <member><citerefentry project='man-pages'><refentrytitle>pam.d</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry></member>
      <member><citerefentry project='man-pages'><refentrytitle>pam</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry></member>
    </simplelist></para>
  </refsect1>

</refentry>
