<?xml version='1.0'?> <!--*-nxml-*-->
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<!--
  SPDX-License-Identifier: LGPL-2.1-or-later

  Copyright © 2023 GNOME Foundation Inc.
        Original Author: Adrian Vovk
-->

<refentry id="systemd-homed-sync-bulk.service" conditional='ENABLE_HOMED'
          xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

  <refentryinfo>
    <title>systemd-homed-sync-bulk.service</title>
    <productname>systemd</productname>
  </refentryinfo>

  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>systemd-homed-sync-bulk.service</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>systemd-homed-bulk-sync.service</refname>
    <refpurpose>Home Area Bulk Directory Sync</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para><filename>systemd-homed-bulk-sync.service</filename></para>
    <para><filename>systemd-homed-bulk-sync.path</filename></para>
    <para><filename>/usr/lib/systemd/systemd-homed-sync-bulk</filename></para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>

    <para><command>systemd-homed-sync-bulk</command> is a user service that synchronizes a user's
    bulk directory between two locations: one in the user's home directory, and another belonging
    to the system. It is run at login and whenever the contents of either directory change.</para>

    <para>The bulk directory is for storing data that conceptually belongs to the user's identity (i.e. their
    <ulink url="https://systemd.io/USER_RECORD/">JSON User Record</ulink>), but is too large to embed directly
    into the JSON. For example: the bulk directory should be used to store a custom profile picture for the user.
    Another example: the bulk directory could be used to store the user's wallpaper, which will then allow the
    system's login UI to display it.</para>

    <para>As mentioned above, there are two copies of the bulk directory that are kept in sync. The first is
    <filename>$XDG_DATA_HOME/homed/</filename> or <filename>$HOME/.local/share/homed/</filename>, which we will
    call the "home bulk" directory. The home bulk directory is only accessible while the user is in an active
    state (i.e. logged in and unlocked). The other copy is found in
    <filename>/var/cache/homed/<replaceable>username</replaceable>/</filename>,
    which we will call the "system bulk" directory. The system bulk directory is only populated a little while
    after a user logs into the system for the first time.</para>

    <para>External software is free to access either the home or system bulk directories, but should prefer to
    access the system bulk directory. This helps avoid situations where files are missing because the two directories
    are synchronized in the background. However, it should still be prepared for missing files; their presence is
    best-effort. Before writing to either directory, exernal software MUST take a <constant>LOCK_EX</constant> BSD file
    lock (<citerefentry project='man-pages'><refentrytitle>flock</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum></citerefentry>)
    on the directory to avoid conflicts with <command>systemd-homed-sync-bulk</command>. If taking locks on both
    directories at the same time, external software MUST lock the system bulk directory before the home bulk
    directory to avoid deadlock.</para>

    <para>Nothing sensitive should be stored in the bulk directories. They are world-readable, and the files inside of
    them should be too. Data deleted from the system directory will still remain in the home directory until the next
    synchronization. Any destructive change such as overwritten or even deleted files might be undone if something
    goes wrong in <command>systemd-homed-sync-bulk</command>, which avoids deleting or overwriting data if it cannot
    determine what it should do. If you wish to be absolutely certain that a destructive change is persisted, you
    should take simultaneous locks on both directories and then make your change in both directories. This, however,
    should not be generally necessary or even recommended: in normal operation, <command>systemd-homed-sync-bulk</command>
    will keep the directories in sync.</para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>See Also</title>
    <para><simplelist type="inline">
      <member><citerefentry><refentrytitle>systemd</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></member>
      <member><citerefentry><refentrytitle>systemd-homed.service</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry></member>
      <member><citerefentry><refentrytitle>homectl</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></member>
    </simplelist></para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
