<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" >
<!-- SPDX-License-Identifier: LGPL-2.1-or-later -->

<refentry id="org.freedesktop.sysupdate1" conditional='ENABLE_SYSUPDATED'
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <refentryinfo>
    <title>org.freedesktop.sysupdate1</title>
    <productname>systemd</productname>
  </refentryinfo>

  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>org.freedesktop.sysupdate1</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>org.freedesktop.sysupdate1</refname>
    <refpurpose>The D-Bus interface of systemd-sysupdated</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>systemd-sysupdated.service</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>
    is a system service that allows unprivileged clients to update the system. This page describes the D-Bus
    interface.</para>

    <para><emphasis>WARNING!</emphasis> This API is currently <emphasis>unstable</emphasis> and is thus subject
    to breaking changes between versions of systemd.</para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>The Manager Object</title>

    <para>The service exposes the following interfaces on the Manager object on the bus:</para>

    <programlisting executable="systemd-sysupdated" node="/org/freedesktop/sysupdate1" interface="org.freedesktop.sysupdate1.Manager">
node /org/freedesktop/sysupdate1 {
  interface org.freedesktop.sysupdate1.Manager {
    methods:
      ListTargets(out a(sso) targets);
      ListJobs(out a(tsuo) jobs);
      ListAppStream(out as urls);
    signals:
      JobRemoved(t id,
                 o path,
                 i status);
  };
  interface org.freedesktop.DBus.Peer { ... };
  interface org.freedesktop.DBus.Introspectable { ... };
  interface org.freedesktop.DBus.Properties { ... };
};
</programlisting>

    <!--Autogenerated cross-references for systemd.directives, do not edit-->

    <variablelist class="dbus-interface" generated="True" extra-ref="org.freedesktop.sysupdate1.Manager"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-interface" generated="True" extra-ref="org.freedesktop.sysupdate1.Manager"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="ListTargets()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="ListJobs()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="ListAppStream()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-signal" generated="True" extra-ref="JobRemoved()"/>

    <!--End of Autogenerated section-->

    <refsect2>
      <title>Methods</title>

      <para><function>ListTargets()</function> returns a list all known update targets. It returns
      an array of structures which consist of a string indicating the target's class (see Target's
      <varname>Class</varname> property below for an explanation of the possible values), a string
      with the name of the target, and the target object path.</para>

      <para><function>ListJobs()</function> returns a list all ongoing jobs. It returns
      an array of structures which consist of a numeric job ID, a string indicating the job type (see Job's
      <varname>Type</varname> property below for an explanation of the possible values), the job's progress,
      and the job's object path.</para>

      <para><function>ListAppStream()</function> returns an array of all the appstream catalog URLs that this
      service knows about. See Target's <varname>GetAppStream()</varname> method below for more
      details.</para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Signals</title>

      <para>The <function>JobRemoved()</function> signal is sent each time a job finishes,
      is canceled or fails. It also carries the job ID and object path, followed by a numeric status
      code. If the status is zero, the job has succeed. A positive status should be treated as an
      exit code (i.e. <literal>EXIT_FAILURE</literal>), and a negative status should be treated as a
      negative errno-style error code (i.e. <literal>-EINVAL</literal>).</para>
    </refsect2>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>The Target Object</title>

    <para>A target is a component of the system (i.e. the host itself, a sysext, a confext, etc.) that
    can be updated by
    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>systemd-sysupdate</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>.
    </para>

    <para>The service exposes the following interfaces on Target objects on the bus:</para>

    <programlisting executable="systemd-sysupdated" node="/org/freedesktop/sysupdate1/target/host" interface="org.freedesktop.sysupdate1.Target">
node /org/freedesktop/sysupdate1/target/host {
  interface org.freedesktop.sysupdate1.Target {
    methods:
      List(in  t flags,
           out as versions);
      Describe(in  s version,
               in  t flags,
               out s json);
      CheckNew(out s new_version);
      Acquire(in  s new_version,
              in  t flags,
              out s new_version,
              out t job_id,
              out o job_path);
      Install(in  s new_version,
              in  t flags,
              out s new_version,
              out t job_id,
              out o job_path);
      Vacuum(out u instances,
             out u disabled_transfers);
      GetAppStream(out as appstream);
      GetVersion(out s version);
      ListFeatures(in  t flags,
                   out as features);
      DescribeFeature(in  s feature,
                      in  t flags,
                      out s json);
      SetFeatureEnabled(in  s feature,
                        in  i enabled,
                        in  t flags);
    properties:
      @org.freedesktop.DBus.Property.EmitsChangedSignal("const")
      readonly s Class = '...';
      @org.freedesktop.DBus.Property.EmitsChangedSignal("const")
      readonly s Name = '...';
      @org.freedesktop.DBus.Property.EmitsChangedSignal("const")
      readonly s Path = '...';
  };
  interface org.freedesktop.DBus.Peer { ... };
  interface org.freedesktop.DBus.Introspectable { ... };
  interface org.freedesktop.DBus.Properties { ... };
};
</programlisting>

    <!--Autogenerated cross-references for systemd.directives, do not edit-->

    <variablelist class="dbus-interface" generated="True" extra-ref="org.freedesktop.sysupdate1.Target"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-interface" generated="True" extra-ref="org.freedesktop.sysupdate1.Target"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="List()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="Describe()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="CheckNew()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="Acquire()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="Install()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="Vacuum()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="GetAppStream()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="GetVersion()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="ListFeatures()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="DescribeFeature()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="SetFeatureEnabled()"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-property" generated="True" extra-ref="Class"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-property" generated="True" extra-ref="Name"/>

    <variablelist class="dbus-property" generated="True" extra-ref="Path"/>

    <!--End of Autogenerated section-->

    <refsect2>
      <title>Methods</title>

      <para><function>List()</function> returns a list of versions available for this target. Additional
      options may be passed through the <varname>flags</varname> argument. Valid flags are defined as follows:
      </para>

      <programlisting>
#define SD_SYSUPDATE_OFFLINE    (UINT64_C(1) &lt;&lt; 0)
</programlisting>

      <para>When <constant>SD_SYSUPDATE_OFFLINE</constant> is set, this method returns only the versions
      installed locally. Otherwise, this method pulls metadata from the network and returns all versions
      available for this target. Use <function>Describe()</function> to query more information about each
      version returned by this method.</para>

      <para><function>Describe()</function> returns all known information about a given version as a JSON
      object. The <varname>version</varname> argument is used to pass the version to be described. Additional
      options may be passed through the <varname>flags</varname> argument. This method supports the same flags
      as <function>List()</function>. The returned JSON object contains several known keys. More keys may be
      added in the future. The currently known keys are as follows:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><literal>version</literal></term>
          <listitem><para>A string containing the version number.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><literal>newest</literal></term>
          <listitem><para>A boolean indicating whether this version is the latest available for the target.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><literal>available</literal></term>
          <listitem><para>A boolean indicating whether this version is available for download.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><literal>installed</literal></term>
          <listitem><para>A boolean indicating whether this version is installed locally.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><literal>obsolete</literal></term>
          <listitem><para>A boolean indicating whether this version is considered obsolete by the service,
          and is therefore disallowed from being installed.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><literal>protected</literal></term>
          <listitem><para>A boolean indicating whether this version is exempt from deletion by a
          <function>Vacuum()</function> operation.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><literal>incomplete</literal></term>
          <listitem><para>A boolean indicating whether this version is incomplete, which means that it is
          missing some file. Note that only installed incomplete versions will be offered by the service;
          versions that are incomplete on the server-side are completely ignored. Incomplete versions can
          be repaired in-place by calling <function>Acquire()</function> and <function>Install()</function>
          on that version.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><literal>changelogUrls</literal></term>
          <listitem><para>A list of strings that contain user-presentable URLs to change logs associated with
          this version.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para><function>CheckNew()</function> checks if a newer version is available for this target. This
      method pulls metadata from the network. If a newer version is found, this method returns the
      version number. If no newer version is found, this method returns an empty string. Use
      <function>Describe()</function> to query more information about the version returned by this method.
      </para>

      <para><function>Acquire()</function> downloads an update for this target, if one is available. If a
      <varname>new_version</varname> is specified, that is the version that gets downloaded. Otherwise, the
      latest version is downloaded. Call <function>Install()</function> to install the acquired update.
      The <varname>flags</varname> argument is added for future extensibility. No flags are currently
      defined, and the argument is required to be set to <literal>0</literal>. This method pulls both
      metadata and payload data from the network.</para>

      <para><function>Install()</function> installs an already-acquired update for this target. If a
      <varname>new_version</varname> is specified, that is the version that gets installed, assuming it has
      already been acquired. Otherwise, the latest acquired version is installed. The
      <varname>flags</varname> argument is added for future extensibility. No flags are currently defined,
      and the argument is required to be set to <literal>0</literal>.</para>

      <para>Unlike all the other methods in this interface, <function>Acquire()</function> and
      <function>Install()</function> do not wait for their jobs to complete. Instead, they return the job's
      numeric ID and object path as soon as the job begins, so that the caller can listen for progress
      updates or cancel the operation. These methods also return the version the target will be updated to,
      for cases where no version was specified by the caller. Listen for the Manager's
      <function>JobRemoved()</function> signal to detect when the job is complete.</para>

      <para><function>Vacuum()</function> deletes old installed versions of this target to free up space.
      It returns the number of instances that have been deleted.</para>

      <para><function>GetAppStream()</function> returns a list of HTTP/HTTPS URLs to this target's
      <ulink url="https://wwww.freedesktop.org/software/appstream/docs/chap-CatalogData.html">appstream catalog</ulink>
      XML files. If this target has no appstream catalogs, the method will return an empty list. These
      catalog files can be used by software centers (such as GNOME Software or KDE Discover) to present rich
      metadata about the target, including a display name, changelog, icon, and more. The returned catalogs
      will include <ulink url="https://systemd.io/APPSTREAM_BUNDLE">special metadata</ulink> to allow the
      software center to correctly associate the catalogs with this target.</para>

      <para><function>GetVersion()</function> returns the current version of this target, if any. The current
      version is the newest version that is installed. Note that this is not necessarily the same thing as the
      booted or currently-in-use version of the target.  For example, on the host system the booted version
      is the current version most of the time, but if an update is installed and pending a reboot it will
      become the current version instead.  You can query the booted version of the host system via
      <varname>IMAGE_VERSION</varname> in <filename>/etc/os-release</filename>. If the target has no current
      version, the function will return an empty string.</para>

      <para><function>ListFeatures()</function> returns a list of this target's optional features, by ID.
      The <varname>flags</varname> argument is added for future extensibility, and must be set to 0.
      If the target has no optional features, the method returns an empty array.</para>

      <para><function>DescribeFeature()</function> returns all known information about a given optional feature.
      The <varname>feature</varname> argument is used to pass the ID of the feature to be described.
      The <varname>flags</varname> argument is added for future extensibility, and must be set to 0.
      The returned JSON object contains several known keys. More keys may be added in the future.
      The currently known keys are as follows:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><literal>name</literal></term>
          <listitem><para>A string containing the feature's name.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><literal>description</literal></term>
          <listitem><para>An optional string that contains a user-presentable description that identifies
          this feature</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><literal>enabled</literal></term>
          <listitem><para>A boolean indicating whether this feature is enabled.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><literal>documentationUrl</literal></term>
          <listitem><para>An optional string that contains a user-presentable HTTP/HTTPS URL to documentation
          about this feature.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><literal>appstreamUrl</literal></term>
          <listitem><para>An optional string that contains an HTTP/HTTPS URL to an
          <ulink url="https://wwww.freedesktop.org/software/appstream/docs/chap-CatalogData.html">appstream
          catalog</ulink> XML file containing metadata about this feature.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><literal>transfers</literal></term>
          <listitem><para>An optional array of strings that list which transfer definitions belong to this
          feature.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para><function>SetFeatureEnabled()</function> writes an appropriate drop-in file to enable or disable
      the specified optional feature.
      If <varname>enable</varname> is zero, the feature is disabled. When greater than zero, the feature is
      enabled. When less than zero, the feature is reset to the distribution's default.
      The <varname>flags</varname> argument is added for future extensibility, and must be set to 0.
      The feature does not have to exist; this allows for graceful handling of masked features, and for
      preemptive decisions to be made about features that are planned to appear in future releases of the OS.
      The drop-in will have a filename of <literal>50-systemd-sysupdate-enabled.conf</literal>.
      This method only changes configuration files; to actually apply the changes, clients will need to
      call <function>Acquire()</function> and <function>Install()</function>.
      Depending on the exact needs of the client, it can choose to update the system to the latest available
      version, or it can extend the newest existing installation in-place (by passing in the version returned
      by <varname>GetVersion()</varname>).
      For now, this method only works with the <literal>host</literal> target.</para>

    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Properties</title>

      <para>The <varname>Class</varname> property exposes the class of this target, which describes
      where it was enumerated. Possible values include: <literal>machine</literal> for containers and
      virtual machines managed by
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>systemd-machined.service</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
      <literal>portable</literal> for <ulink url="https://systemd.io/PORTABLE_SERVICES">portable services</ulink>,
      <literal>sysext</literal> for system extensions managed by
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>systemd-sysext</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
      <literal>confext</literal> for configuration extensions managed by
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>systemd-confext</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
      <literal>component</literal> for components accepted by the <option>--component=</option> option of
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>systemd-sysupdate</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
      and <literal>host</literal> for the host system itself. At most one target will have a class of
      <literal>host</literal>.</para>

      <para>The <varname>Path</varname> property exposes more detail about where this target was found.
      For <literal>machine</literal>, <literal>portable</literal>, <literal>extension</literal>, and
      <literal>confext</literal> targets, this is the file path to the image. For <literal>component</literal>
      and <literal>host</literal> targets, this is the name of a
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>sysupdate.d</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry>
      directory.</para>

      <para>The <varname>Name</varname> property exposes the name of this target. Note that the name is
      unique within a class but is not necessarily unique between classes. For instance, it is possible
      to have both a <literal>portable</literal> target named <literal>foobar</literal> and an
      <literal>extension</literal> target named <literal>foobar</literal>, but it is not possible to have
      two <literal>portable</literal> targets named <literal>foobar</literal>.</para>

    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Security</title>

      <para>Method calls on this service are authenticated via
      <ulink url="https://www.freedesktop.org/software/polkit/docs/latest/">polkit</ulink>.</para>

      <para><function>List()</function>, <function>Describe()</function>, and <function>CheckNew()</function>
      use the polkit action <interfacename>org.freedesktop.sysupdate1.check</interfacename>.
      By default, this action is permitted without administrator authentication.</para>

      <para><function>Acquire()</function> and <function>Install()</function>
      use the polkit action
      <interfacename>org.freedesktop.sysupdate1.update</interfacename> when no version is specified.
      By default, this action is permitted without administrator authentication. When a version is
      specified, <interfacename>org.freedesktop.sysupdate1.update-to-version</interfacename> is
      used instead. By default, this alternate action requires administrator authentication.</para>

      <para><function>Vacuum()</function> uses the polkit action
      <interfacename>org.freedesktop.sysupdate1.vacuum</interfacename>. By default, this action requires
      administrator authentication.</para>

      <para><function>SetFeatureEnabled()</function> uses the polkit action
      <interfacename>org.freedesktop.sysupdate1.manage-features</interfacename>. By default, this action
      requires administrator authentication.</para>

      <para><function>GetAppStream()</function>, <function>GetVersion()</function>,
      <function>ListFeatures()</function>, and <function>DescribeFeature()</function>
      are unauthenticated and may be called by anybody.</para>

      <para>All methods called on this interface expose additional variables to the polkit rules.
      <literal>class</literal> contains the class of the Target being acted upon, and <literal>name</literal>
      contains the name of the same Target. Additionally, each method exposes its arguments to the
      rule. Flags are mapped as follows:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para><constant>SD_SYSUPDATE_OFFLINE</constant> → <literal>update</literal></para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    </refsect2>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>The Job Object</title>

    <para>A job is an ongoing operation, started by one of the methods on a Target object.</para>

    <para>The service exposes the following interfaces on Job objects on the bus:</para>

    <programlisting executable="systemd-sysupdated" node="/org/freedesktop/sysupdate1/job/_1" interface="org.freedesktop.sysupdate1.Job">
node /org/freedesktop/sysupdate1/job/_1 {
  interface org.freedesktop.sysupdate1.Job {
    methods:
      Cancel();
    properties:
      @org.freedesktop.DBus.Property.EmitsChangedSignal("const")
      readonly t Id = ...;
      @org.freedesktop.DBus.Property.EmitsChangedSignal("const")
      readonly s Type = '...';
      @org.freedesktop.DBus.Property.EmitsChangedSignal("const")
      readonly b Offline = ...;
      readonly u Progress = ...;
  };
  interface org.freedesktop.DBus.Peer { ... };
  interface org.freedesktop.DBus.Introspectable { ... };
  interface org.freedesktop.DBus.Properties { ... };
};
</programlisting>


    <!--Autogenerated cross-references for systemd.directives, do not edit-->


    <variablelist class="dbus-interface" generated="True" extra-ref="org.freedesktop.sysupdate1.Job"/>


    <variablelist class="dbus-interface" generated="True" extra-ref="org.freedesktop.sysupdate1.Job"/>


    <variablelist class="dbus-method" generated="True" extra-ref="Cancel()"/>


    <variablelist class="dbus-property" generated="True" extra-ref="Id"/>


    <variablelist class="dbus-property" generated="True" extra-ref="Type"/>


    <variablelist class="dbus-property" generated="True" extra-ref="Offline"/>


    <variablelist class="dbus-property" generated="True" extra-ref="Progress"/>


    <!--End of Autogenerated section-->


    <refsect2>
      <title>Methods</title>

      <para>The <function>Cancel()</function> method may be used to cancel the job. It takes no
      parameters.</para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Properties</title>

      <para>The <varname>Id</varname> property exposes the numeric job ID of the job object.</para>

      <para>The <varname>Type</varname> property exposes the type of operation (one of:
      <literal>list</literal>, <literal>describe</literal>, <literal>check-new</literal>,
      <literal>acquire</literal>, <literal>install</literal>, <literal>vacuum</literal>, or
      <literal>describe-feature</literal>).</para>

      <para>The <varname>Offline</varname> property exposes whether the job is permitted to access
      the network or not.</para>

      <para>The <varname>Progress</varname> property exposes the current progress of the job as a value
      between 0 and 100. It is only available for <literal>acquire</literal> and <literal>install</literal>
      jobs; for all other jobs it is always 0.</para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Security</title>

      <para><function>Cancel()</function> uses the polkit action that corresponds to the method
      that started this job. For instance, trying to cancel a <literal>list</literal> job will
      require polkit to permit the <interfacename>org.freedesktop.sysupdate1.check</interfacename>
      action.</para>
    </refsect2>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>

    <example>
      <title>Introspect <interfacename>org.freedesktop.sysupdate1.Manager</interfacename> on the bus</title>

      <programlisting>$ gdbus introspect --system \
  --dest org.freedesktop.sysupdate1 \
  --object-path /org/freedesktop/sysupdate1
</programlisting>
    </example>

    <example>
      <title>Introspect <interfacename>org.freedesktop.sysupdate1.Target</interfacename> on the bus</title>

      <programlisting>$ gdbus introspect --system \
  --dest org.freedesktop.sysupdate1 \
  --object-path /org/freedesktop/sysupdate1/target/host
</programlisting>
    </example>

    <example>
      <title>Introspect <interfacename>org.freedesktop.sysupdate1.Job</interfacename> on the bus</title>

      <programlisting>$ gdbus introspect --system \
  --dest org.freedesktop.sysupdate1 \
  --object-path /org/freedesktop/sysupdate1/job/_1
</programlisting>
    </example>
  </refsect1>

  <xi:include href="org.freedesktop.locale1.xml" xpointer="versioning"/>
  <refsect1>
    <title>History</title>
    <refsect2>
      <title>The Manager Object</title>
      <para><function>ListTargets()</function>,
      <function>ListJobs()</function>,
      <function>ListAppStream()</function>, and
      <function>JobRemoved()</function> were added in version 257.</para>
    </refsect2>
    <refsect2>
      <title>The Target Object</title>
      <para><function>List()</function>,
      <function>Describe()</function>,
      <function>CheckNew()</function>,
      <function>Acquire()</function>,
      <function>Install()</function>,
      <function>Vacuum()</function>,
      <function>GetAppStream()</function>,
      <function>GetVersion()</function>,
      <function>ListFeatures()</function>,
      <function>DescribeFeature()</function>,
      <function>SetFeatureEnabled()</function>,
      <varname>Class</varname>,
      <varname>Name</varname>, and
      <varname>Path</varname> were added in version 257.</para>
    </refsect2>
    <refsect2>
      <title>The Job Object</title>
      <para><function>Cancel()</function>,
      <varname>Id</varname>,
      <varname>Type</varname>,
      <varname>Offline</varname>, and
      <varname>Progress</varname> were added in version 257.</para>
    </refsect2>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>See Also</title>
    <para><simplelist type="inline">
      <member><citerefentry><refentrytitle>systemd</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></member>
      <member><citerefentry><refentrytitle>systemd-sysupdated.service</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry></member>
      <member><citerefentry><refentrytitle>updatectl</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></member>
    </simplelist></para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
